<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present interest of England in matters of religion, stated wherein is clearly demonstrated that the Protestant religion may be fully secured from popery, though the penal laws be taken away / by W.D., alover of liberty for conscience sake.</title>
            <author>W. D., lover of liberty for conscience sake.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D99</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57825</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37536)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57825)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 179:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present interest of England in matters of religion, stated wherein is clearly demonstrated that the Protestant religion may be fully secured from popery, though the penal laws be taken away / by W.D., alover of liberty for conscience sake.</title>
                  <author>W. D., lover of liberty for conscience sake.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57825:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57825:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Preſent Intereſt OF ENGLAND IN Matters of Religion, Stated.</p>
            <p>Wherein is clearly demonſtrated that the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> may be fully ſecured from <hi>Popery,</hi> though the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> be taken away.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. D.</hi> a Lover of Liberty for Conſcience ſake.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 2.7.</hi>
               </bibl> He that hath an ear to hear let him hear.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> and ſold by moſt Bookſellers. 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:57825:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57825:2"/>
            <head>The Preſent Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, ſtated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BOoks are now written to inſtruct the preſent Age, and to inform the future; that this may know what ought to be done, and that may ſee what has been done; and in this lies the great skill and wiſdom of good men, to know and underſtand the work of God in their day, that they may be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers together with God, and workers together with him,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.9.</note> and ſerve their generation by the will of God.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> Sometimes men do not know, nor underſtand the work of God in their day. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſtaid ſo long in <hi>Canaan</hi> till he wanted bread; God ſent a Famine upon that Land, that <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Family might go down to <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to eat bread to the full. God remembred him in his low eſtate, but he remembred not the mighty works of God that he had ſeen, nor that experience he had of his love and grace, his mercies and goodneſs that had followed him all along; he looked upon the providences of God, and they ſeem'd to run croſs to the promiſes; he looked upon the work of God, and that ſeem'd to be ſo dark, that he could ſee no beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nor glory in it: He looked upon the things that then befel him, and they ſeem'd to work together for his hurt: And <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>All theſe things are againſt me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 42.36.</note> He look't upon <hi>Simeon</hi> that was left behind in <hi>Egypt,</hi> to be a dead man, Joſeph <hi>is not, and</hi> Simeon <hi>is not,</hi> and the going down of <hi>Benjamin</hi> with the reſt of his Brethren, to be nothing but a trick and a deſign of the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to get all his Sons into their hands, that they might be Bondmen and Slaves at the leaſt: And he ſaid, <hi>Me have ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved of my Children.</hi> When <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaw the glory of God's
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57825:3"/>work appear, then he rejoyced; but the way to that glory he did not underſtand. Now that which God intended and deſigned by all this, was the fulfilling of his word, the glory of his holy name, the increaſe of his Church, that he might make of them a great Nation, as he had promiſed. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Abraham, <hi>Know of a ſurety, that thy Seed ſhall be a ſtranger in a Land that is not theirs, and ſhall ſerve them, and they ſhall afflict them four hundred years, and alſo that Nation whom they ſhall ſerve, will I judge, and afterwards ſhall they come out with great ſubſtance,</hi> Gen. 15.13, 14. When men do not underſtand the work of God in their day, then they cenſure, and arraign, and condemn that wiſdom and power, that love and grace, that goodneſs and mercy, that is moving towards them, and breaking in upon them. God can do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he pleaſeth, and he will do whatſoever he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
            <p>Sometimes men leave the work of God, and forſake it, and turn their backs upon it, after they have been ingaged in it.<note place="margin">Numb. 13.26.</note> So did the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they were in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of <hi>Paran.</hi> God had taken them out of the Iron Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and had brought them up from the Houſe of Bondage, and ſaved them from the Swords of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and ſeal'd his truth to them by Miracles and Wonders in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as they paſt along. <hi>And now they being come near</hi> Canaan, <hi>the Lord commanded them by</hi> Moſes, <hi>to go in and poſſeſs that good Land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>a Land that flowed with Milk and Honey, the glorious Land, and the glory of all Lands.</hi> And this was the work of God in that day, but they rebelled againſt the Lord, and would not hearken unto his voice. <hi>And all the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>murmured againſt</hi> Moſes, <hi>and againſt</hi> Aaron: <hi>and the whole Congregation ſaid unto them, Would God that we had died in the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>or would God we had died in this Wilderneſs; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath the Lord brought us unto this Land, to fall by the Sword, that our Wives and our Children ſhould be a prey? Were it not better for us to return into</hi> Egypt? <hi>And they ſaid one to another, Let us make a Captain, and let us return into</hi> Egypt, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.2, 3, 4. You ſee here they were for <hi>Egypt,</hi> and not <hi>Canaan:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57825:3"/>For a new Captain to lead them, and not <hi>Moſes:</hi> For Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and Slavery, and not Liberty and Freedom: And God Almighty took them at their word. <hi>As truly as I live ſaith the Lord, as ye have ſpoken in mine Ears, ſo will I do to you. Your Carcaſes ſhall fall in this Wilderneſs, and all that were numbred of you, according to your whole number from twenty years old and upward which have murmured againſt me, verſe</hi> 28, 29. Their <hi>Egypt</hi> was the Wilderneſs, their Captain was their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and forty years was the time of their miſery. <hi>But with many of them God was not well-pleaſed, for they were overthrown in the Wilderneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.5.</note> They that will not hear the word of God that is ſpoken to them, ſhall feel the wrath of God that is ſpoken of them. There is a way of flying to God, but there is no way of flying from God.</p>
            <p>Sometimes men deſpiſe the work of God, and look upon it as a very ſmall thing, not worthy of their acceptance; this did the <hi>Jews</hi> that were in Captivity, which <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had carried away from the land of <hi>Judea</hi> to <hi>Babylon. And after they had been there threeſcore and ten years,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.21.</note> the Lord ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up the ſpirit of</hi> Cyrus <hi>King of</hi> Perſia, <hi>that he made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation thoughout all his Kingdom, and put it alſo in Writing, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Who is there among you of all his people? His God be with him, and let him go up to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>which is in</hi> Judah, <hi>and Build the Houſe of the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>he is the God which is in</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. <hi>And whoſoever remaineth in any place where he ſojourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth let the men of his place help him with Silver, and with Gold, and with Goods, and with Beaſts, beſides the Free-will Offering for the Houſe of God that is in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.1, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>Now what did theſe <hi>Jews</hi> do after they had ſeen the Kings Proclamation, which was ſo full of Love and Goodneſs? Did they go up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and Build the Houſe of God? Their Yokes were now broken, their Bands were looſed, their heavy Burdens were removed, Liberty was proclaimed, a Door was opened of Mercy and Grace, the Call of God was clear, the Work of God was great and glorious.<note place="margin">Ezra 7.7. Ezra 1.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Some of them did go up.</hi> They were only them whoſe ſpirits God had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57825:4"/>rais'd to go up; but the moſt of them did not, as appear'd afterwards by <hi>Haman</hi>'s Plot, <hi>Eſther 3.8, 9. And</hi> Haman <hi>ſaid unto King</hi> Ahaſuerus, <hi>there is a certain people ſcattered abroad, and diſpers'd among the people, in all the Provinces of thy Kingdom, and their Laws are diverſe from all people, neither keep they the Kings Laws; therefore it is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them. If it pleaſe the King let it be written that they may be deſtroy'd, and I will pay ten Thouſand Talents of Silver to the hands of thoſe that have the charge of the buſineſs.</hi> How ſad is it then not to follow the call of God? Theſe <hi>Jews</hi> lookt upon the Way up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be long, the Journey dangerous, the Succeſs doubtful, the King a Heathen, the Enemy there before, and therefore they deſpiſed the work of God, and prefer'd their eaſe before glory, and bondage before freedom, and their little concerns before the great and glorious work of God. They choſe rather to dwell amongſt the Heathens, and to ſee their abominable Idolatry, than to go up with their Brethren to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to worſhip the Lord. When men take their meaſures from their fears, and jealouſies, and not from the word of God, and his providences: When men conſult with Fleſh and Blood, and not the duty of their places, and the work of God that lyes before them: When men lean to their own underſtandings, and reject the counſel of God: When men rely upon an Arm of Fleſh, and not upon the mighty God of <hi>Jacob;</hi> then they do deſpiſe the work of God in their day, and cry it down, and endeavour to bring an evil report upon it, ſaying, Ah, this is not the time, this is not the way, theſe are not fit inſtruments to be imploy'd. O vain man, know and conſider, that Gods power is irreſiſtible, his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom unſearchable, and his ways paſt finding out. Sin at the firſt was the cauſe of all ignorance, but now ignorance is the cauſe of all ſin. Our work below is then the beſt done, when our work above is the firſt done.</p>
            <p>Sometimes men reſiſt the work of God, and oppoſe it in their day, and ſeek to overthrow it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This the perſecuting <hi>Jews</hi> did in the days of our Saviour, and in the days of the Apoſtles. <hi>For this man doth many Miracles;<note place="margin">Acts 5.39.</note> if we let this man alone, all men will believe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57825:4"/>on him, and the</hi> Romans <hi>ſhall come and take away both our place and nation, John</hi> 11.47, 48. Theſe words were ſpoken in Counſel, and the deſign of them was to overthrow the work of God, to perſecute Chriſt Jeſus to death, and his faithful Witneſſes. <hi>Then from that day forth they took Counſel together for to put him to death, verſe</hi> 53. he came and preached peace to them, but they proclaimed War againſt him. He came to his own, but they received him not. He came to heal them, but they wounded him. He came to ſave them, but they killed him. He was full of love, grace, and truth, but they were filled with rage, malice, prejudice, and unbelief. They clipped the wings of his mercy, and clogged the wheels of his love and kindneſs. They ſhut up the treaſures of his grace againſt themſelves, and held the hand of his power by their unbelief. <hi>And he did not many mighty works there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their unbelief, Matth.</hi> 13.58. That which the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid then, the unbelieving <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſay now. We will not have this man to reign over us. Sin and Satan ſhall reign, the Law and the Letter ſhall reign: But he that is Lord of life, and gives life, ſhall not reign over us. The ways and methods that the <hi>Jews</hi> took to keep the <hi>Romans</hi> out, brought the <hi>Romans</hi> in upon them. For they perſecuted Gods Faithful Servants, and commanded them not to preach the Goſpel, not to ſpeak in his name, and that brought the wrath of God upon them. <hi>Forbidding us to ſpeak to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>that they might be ſaved, to fill up their ſins alway: For the wrath is come upon them to the uttermoſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.16. When men take evil ways to ſave themſelves from the evil they fear, that may come and may not come, it is the ready way to bring that evil upon them they fear. <hi>Take therefore no thought for the morrow, for the morrow ſhall take thought for the things of it ſelf: ſufficient unto the day is the evil thereof, Matth.</hi> 6.34. When we make God our refuge, and ſtrength, then he makes Heaven our inheritance, and the Earth our paſſage to that glorious inheritance.</p>
            <p>I have in the firſt place ſhew'd you what was done hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Jews, and what that work of God was in their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57825:5"/>days; <hi>For whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures might have hope, Romans</hi> 15.4. And now in the ſecond place I ſhall ſhew you, what that work of God is in our day, that you that know may know more, and do the things that are Juſt, and beſt for your ſelves, and others. This then is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold work.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Salvation Work.</item>
               <item>2. A Generation Work.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt a Salvation Work. <hi>Work out your Salvation with fear and trembling, Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>I muſt work the works of him that ſent me, while it is day: the night cometh wherein no man can work, John</hi> 9.4. Death is a work, but wants to be done. the doing of it well then, will require now our utmoſt endeavours, our greateſt diligence, our always abounding in the work of the Lord, a conſidering of our ways, a right ordering of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, a running the race that is ſet before us, a ſtriving to enter in at the ſtrait gate, a giving all diligence to make our calling and election ſure, a growing in grace, and a laying up a good foundation againſt the time to come, and a labouring for that bread that periſheth not. O conſider this, that Heaven, and Hell, will divide between them all the people that are now living upon the earth in a little time; every man muſt ſhoot the Gulf of Eternity at Death, and then another Gulf will be fixed. <hi>And beſides all this, between us and you there is a great gulf fixed, ſo that they which would paſs from hence to you, cannot, neither can they paſs to us that would come from thence, Luke</hi> 16.26. They that dye in their ſins, God will never return to them to ſhew mercy, and they ſhall never return to him to receive mercy. O work therefore while it is called to day, the day of mercy is yet continued, and the day of grace is not yet ended: he that will dye but once, muſt dye daily: he that will be delivered from the ſecond Death, muſt have a part in the firſt Reſurrection: He that will be equal with Saints in Glory, muſt be eminent with Saints in Grace. No Souls can live with God in Heaven, but ſuch in whom the Spirit of God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57825:5"/>lived whiles they were on Earth. They that neglect the work of their Salvation, cannot eſcape the puniſhment of their Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation? Heb.</hi> 2.3. This is the work that every man ſhould moſt purſue, and that early, and not to refer it, and put it off to a dying hour. O how unfit a time is that for ſo great a work? Often-times Mens Speech is taken from them, they would ſpeak, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; ſometimes their reaſon is taken from them, they are light-headed, and ſpeak they know not what; ſurely that is not a proper ſeaſon for men to make their peace with God. Can any man think that God Almighty will be ſo ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to him, that hath lived a ſinful wicked life all his days, when he lyes on his death bed, under the weight of all his ſins when wrath is in his boſom, and vengeance at his back? I was told lately of a rich man, that ſpake theſe words on his bed, a little before he dyed; <hi>I have left thouſands for this Child, and thouſands for that Child, but I have no treaſures laid up for my ſelf in Heaven. To make them Rich, I have made my ſelf Poor: to make them great, I have made my ſelf miſerable; and now my poor Soul is left to ſhift for it ſelf, what will become of it I know not.</hi> O is not this the ſad ſtate and condition of many a Rich Man when he comes to dye? A great man may enjoy much, and yet he wants more than he enjoys; he wants the favour of God, an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Jeſus Chriſt, and that joy of the holy Ghoſt which is unſpeakable, and full of glory, and that love of God, which is better than life, and that grace which is ſufficient, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of that glory which God hath promiſed, and Chriſt hath purchaſed. <hi>O work while it is day, for the night cometh when no man can work.</hi> When once the Maſter of the Houſe is riſen up, and hath ſhut to the door, and ye begin to ſtand without, and to knock at the door, ſaying, <hi>Lord, Lord open unto us, and he ſhall anſwer and ſay unto you, I know you not whence you are. Depart from me, ye workers of iniquity. Luke</hi> 13.25, 26, 27. O be therefore traders for heaven, that God may be your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Chriſt your gain, Heaven your home, and Glory your reward. <hi>This then is the work of your Salvation to continue in well-doing, ſeeking for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>and Eternal Life: But Glory, Honour and Peace to every one,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57825:6"/>that worketh good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>For there is no reſpect of perſons with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, A Generation Work. And you will ſay, What is that? Have you not known, have you not heard, has it not been told you? God Almighty hath ſpoken to theſe Nations from Heaven, by his mighty works which we have all ſeen: and the Trumpet of his providences hath ſounded this truth aloud in our ears: <hi>To looſe the bands of wickedneſs, to undo the heavy burthens, and to let the oppreſſed go free, and that ye break every Yoke, Iſaiah</hi> 58.6.</p>
            <p>Who is there amongſt us, that hath not heard this voice? The King that ſits upon the Throne hath ſpoken to us, by his late gracious Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience. <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel</hi> by one argument ſilenced a whole aſſembly of perſecutors, that had agreed to ſlay the Holy Apoſtles. <hi>And they took Counſel together to ſlay them, Acts</hi> 5.33. <hi>Gamaliels</hi> argument was this: <hi>Now I ſay unto you, Refrain from theſe men, and let them alone: for if this counſel, or this work be of men, it will come to nought: but if it be of God ye cannot overthrow it, leſt haply ye be found even to fight againſt God, verſe</hi> 38, 39. Now the King by his gracious Declaration hath done much more, for he hath ſilenced all the perſecutors in three Kingdoms, and tyed up their hands, that they cannot ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs: Many Thouſands of Gods people in theſe Kingdoms have ſpoken alſo to you, by the many humble addreſſes they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King, bleſſing God, and thanking the King for this Liberty of Conſcience which they now enjoy. Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a thing ſo ill in its nature, ſo black in its name, ſo bad in its effects and conſequences, ſo diſpleaſing to God, ſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to a Kingdom, and ſo deſtructive to trade, that modeſty it ſelf might reſtrain men from that helliſh and deviliſh work, though they had nothing of Chriſtianity in them: and this will appear farther, becauſe, <hi>Bleſſed are they, which are perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven, Matth.</hi> 5.10. Now if they be bleſſed, that are perſecuted, then they that perſecute are curſed. If Heaven be the reward of faithful ſufferers for Conſcience ſake towards God, then Hell will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57825:6"/>be the portion of perſecutors.<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.6.</note> If perſecution be a thing ſo evil and bad, let us conſider then what theſe Penal Laws and Teſts are; and what they have done, or has been done by them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then, Theſe Penal Laws have arm'd your Enemies, and put Weapons into their Hands to deſtroy you that are Diſſenters. When you were in the hands of your perſecutors, they neither pity'd you, nor ſpar'd you; but broke open your Doors, and entered into your Houſes, taking away your Money and Goods, and at ſome places not leaving the Poor People a Bed to lye on, nor a Stool to ſit on: forcing you to attend from Seſſions to Seſſions, and from Aſſize to Aſſize, ſtill keeping them bound over, and putting many into Priſon, and there keeping them long, and ſome ſo long till they dy'd. And at that time they told you, that it was not they that ſpoil'd you of your goods, but the Laws: it was not they that ſhut you up in Priſon, but the Laws: it was not they that puniſh'd and deſtroy'd you for your Conſciences towards God, but the Laws. This was that perſecutors ſaid then, and this is that they ſay now, it was the Laws that deſtroyed you, and not them. The King by his Declaration hath put Violence out of their Hands, that they cannot hurt you; and do you pray to God that he might put Violence out of their Hearts, that they may not hate you; and take hold of this opportunity that God hath put into your Hands, by all Juſt and Lawful means, that thoſe Laws may be deſtroy'd, that have deſtroy'd ſo many people. This makes men bold to commit the greateſt wickedneſs, when they have Laws to encourage them, and bear them out. This ſaid the <hi>Jews</hi> that Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered our Lord and Saviour,<note place="margin">John 19.7.</note> 
               <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to dye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.15.</note> And this was the thing that caſt <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Den of Lyons, namely <hi>the Law of the Medes and Perſians.</hi> And this was that encourag'd <hi>Haman</hi> to contrive the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and ruin of ſo many thouſand <hi>Jews</hi> at once;<note place="margin">Eſther 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>The Law being on his ſide, and againſt them.</hi> And this is that the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> complain'd of, <hi>That the Statutes of</hi> Omri <hi>were kept up, and all the works of the houſe of</hi> Ahab, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.16.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57825:7"/>Now if the Penal Laws be ſo hurtful, who then can plead for their continuance?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly theſe Penal Laws have given great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Informers: Good men will not labour for nothing, and bad men will ſtick at nothing: All is Fiſh that comes to their Net, and they will Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h though they catch the Devil, and their own damnation together: Theſe Laws allowing the Informer a third part of the money that is got from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.14, 15.</note> that go to quiet and peaceable Meetings, there to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord in ſpirit and in truth. <hi>Judas</hi> for the love of thirty pieces of ſilver ſold his Lord and Maſter into the hands of Betrayers and Murderers.<note place="margin">Eſth. 3.9, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> to gain ten thouſand Talents of ſilver conſented, and commanded that the beſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all his Kingdom ſhould be deſtroy'd by cruel and bloody hands. <hi>Achan</hi> to purchaſe a Wedge of Gold, and ſome ſilver, brought upon himſelf and Family deſtruction; and troubled, and diſquieted all <hi>Iſrael.</hi> By this you may ſee what men will do, when there is money in the caſe: Theſe Penal Laws did ſet a great many hands at work, but none were ſo induſtrious as the Informers, for that ſort of Vermine crawl'd up and down every where, and were a plague to all people wherever they came; hunting and ſearching up and down to find out Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that they might prey upon the people, and get what money they could from them: And this was their Trade to ſet up a work-houſe for Hell. Now when the Penal Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes are taken away, this Trade will be for ever deſtroy'd. Who will plead for theſe Penal Laws that they may be kept up? ſurely none, but they that had a hand in robbing and ſpoiling their poor Neighbours.<note place="margin">1. Joh. 5.15.</note> In the ſenſe of the Apoſtle <hi>John, Whoſoever hateth his Brother is a murderer; and ye know that no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi> You may ſee by this Text who are the Murderers: And if men ſhall be ſent away with a Curſe into Everlaſting Fire for not relieving and comforting the People of God, when they were in diſtreſs, and ſought unto them that were full, and rich, but they had no bowels of compaſſion in them: What do you think will become of them at that day, that have robb'd and ſpoil'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57825:7"/>the People of God in this day? Oh that ſuch men would give glory to God by Repentance, and ſatisfaction to their poor Neighbours by an acknowledgment to them of the wrong they have done them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Reaſon why theſe Penal Laws ought to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, is this; becauſe they have deſtroy'd Religion, and open'd a door to let in Debauchery and Prophaneneſs upon the People of theſe Lands; the ſad effects of which we ſee at this day. Religion is the glory of a People, the intereſt of a Kingdom, and that which exalts a Nation.<note place="margin">Prov. 14.34.</note> Now that which deſtroys religious men, deſtroys Religion: but that theſe Penal Laws have deſtroyed great numbers of religious People ſince they were made, is evident and plain to all that know any thing: Theſe Penal Statutes have been the Fiery Serpents that have ſlung and bit the People of God as they paſt on their way through this Wilderneſs to the heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 21.6.</note> Theſe have been the Thorns in their ſides, that have prick'd and ſcratch'd many: Theſe have been a Yoke, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther us, nor our Fore-fathers were able to bear. Becauſe that <hi>Amalek</hi> fell upon God's <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as they paſt along in the way, God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>write this for a memorial in a Book, and rehearſe it in the ears of</hi> Joſhua; <hi>for I will utterly put out the remembrance of</hi> Amalek <hi>from under Heaven, Exod</hi> 17.14. King <hi>Saul</hi> had a commiſſion from God to do this work; <hi>Go and ſmite</hi> Amalek, <hi>and utterly deſtroy all that they have, and ſpare them not, but ſlay both Man and Woman, Infant and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Ox and Sheep, Camel and Aſs:</hi> But <hi>Saul</hi> did not do this work ſo fully, as God had commanded him, and therefore he loſt two Kingdoms, an earthly Kingdom, and an heavenly Kingdom; firſt his Life, and then his Soul, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3, 23, 26, 28. Perſecutors are but one people in all Ages; they riſe up in the Spirit of <hi>Cain,</hi> and allow of the deeds of their Fore-fathers; and are the Children of them which have killed the Prophets, and are guilty of all the righteous blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed upon the Earth, from the blood of righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the blood of the laſt murdered Saint. This blood hath cryed long, and loud for vengeance on Perſecutors, and God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57825:8"/>Almighty will give a full, and ſpeedy anſwer to it; this will be but a bad plea for Men, when they ſhall appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Almighty God, nor but little comfort to them in this world, when they are on a ſick Bed, that they had Laws for what they did. For if a Law be ſinful, and bad, as theſe Penal Laws are, this will not bear a man out. The Jews were under Righteous Laws, and yet wicked: But theſe men have deſtroy'd the Righteous by Wicked Laws: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd them in their Eſtates, deſtroy'd them in their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, deſtroy'd them in their Relations, and deſtroy'd many in their Lives: By this you may ſee what theſe Penal Laws are. O let all good Men ſay of theſe Penal Laws, as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Agag; And</hi> Samuel <hi>ſaid, As thy Sword hath made Women childleſs, ſo ſhall thy Mother be childleſs among Women,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.33.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, Theſe Laws which are called Penal Laws, have deſtroyed Liberty, and Property: that which was ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Joel,</hi> concerning the Caterpillers, and Locuſts, and Palmer-Worms, and Canker-Worms, the ſame may be ſaid of theſe Penal Laws: <hi>That which the Palmer-Worm hath left, hath the Locuſt eaten, and that which the Locuſt hath left, hath the Canker-Worm eaten, and that which the Canker-Worm hath left, hath the Caterpiller eaten, Joel</hi> 1.4. Now this was a Judgment that was upon the Land, and a Plague upon the People of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> all this may be truly apply'd to the caſe in hand; for what one Law left, the other took, and amongſt them ſwept away all that the people had; that of twenty pound a month took away their Property, and for not coming to the Sacrament they loſt their Liberty by another Law, and a third ſhut them up in Priſon during Life, and a fourth if they would not abjure, and leave the Land, then they were to be hang'd up as Felons. Theſe were your Penal Statutes, that were then put in force and execution againſt you; are theſe Statutes fit to be kept up now, think you? Where is the man that would be impo'd upon himſelf, and forc'd, and compell'd? where is the man that would be perſecuted, and oppreſs'd, and robb'd of his Liberty,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57825:8"/>and Property? Every man values that at a high rate, and all partys are for Liberty; every man is for Liberty for himſelf, and his own party, though he will not allow it to others: now if all men would but walk by this rule, do as they would be done by, do as they would have others do unto them, mete that meaſure to others as they would have others to mete unto them, and to love their Neighbours as themſelves; for upon this hangs the Law, and the Prophets, it is a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the Law: <hi>For the Law is fulfil'd in one word, even in this, thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, Gal.</hi> 5.14. If men did but duely obſerve, and keep this, then they would not be ſo fond, and deſirous to keep up compelling, and perſecuting Laws.</p>
            <p>But I proceed to the fifth, and that is this:</p>
            <p n="5">5. That theſe Penal Laws have deſtroyed Love and Charity among Men; a thing much to be deſired, and highly to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued. When theſe Laws lay aſleep, and were not put in force, how peaceably and quietly did one Neighbour live by another, how ſweetly and friendly did one man converſe with each other? But no ſooner did that Brat of Hell, and of the Devil (Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) come amongſt us, but it put the whole Nation in a flame, like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes that did ſet all on fire they came near;<note place="margin">Judg. 15.4, 5.</note> then it was nothing but Whig and Tory, Trimmer and Papiſt in Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querade: And in this firmentation was the Nation in, till the King's Gracious Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience, came forth flying amongſt us: That quench'd, and put out theſe fires, that the Penal Laws had kindled: It brought peace to them that were in trouble, eaſe to them that were weary, and relief to them that were in diſtreſs: It looſed the bands of them that were bound over, and open'd the Priſon doors to them that were ſhut up, and ſent Labourers into the Lord's Vineyard that ſtood ſtill; it put violence out of the hands of them that deſtroy'd, and it filled the hearts of many with joy, and their mouths with praiſes and thankſgiving: Firſt to God Almighty, and then to the King, for his great Wiſdom, Juſtice, Mercy, Goodneſs and Kindneſs towards his poor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57825:9"/>Subjects. The good effects of this all good men ſee, and rejoyce in. Now if theſe Penal Laws were the great Make-bate amongſt the People, then the taking of them away will ſlay that enmity, and bury all theſe reproachful names, and terms, that men have caſt upon one another.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In the ſixth place, Perſecution is that which diſcourageth Trade, and greatly deſtroys it: It was that which brought the Trade into <hi>England,</hi> and it is that which will carry the Trade out of <hi>England.</hi> The Perſecution that was heretofore in other Lands, made the Trading-people flie over into theſe Lands, who ſhewed the people here, the way of making theſe Manufactures, that are now made in ſuch abundance, and have proved ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and beneficial to theſe Kingdoms: This is ſo well known, that it cannot be denyed. Now the ſame way that brought the Trade to us, will certainly carry it from us. When theſe Penal Laws were put in force, did not many Trades-men leave the Land, and Merchants, and others in ſeveral Cities in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom did leave their habitations, and were forced to remove to other places, becauſe of the Perſecution that was then? This is well known to moſt men. Now as Righteouſneſs exalts a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo Trade enricheth a Nation. A proof of this you may ſee, if you look over into <hi>Holland,</hi> they granting Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to all Perſuaſions; this brought them a Trade, and that Trade hath made them ſo great, and rich, that as it were from a ſmall Worm, they are become a great Mountain, and from being Poor Diſtreſſed States, they now call themſelves the High and Mighty; from begging, and craving help of others to ſupport them, their Trade hath ſo ſupported them, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their wealth and ſtrength, that they ſtrive to graſp the Trade of Nations into their own hands? Now all theſe bleſſings they ſuck'd from the Breaſt of Liberty of Conſcience. Trade is a great part of the glory of a Nation: It fills the King's Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers with Treaſure (the Cuſtom being one of the Jewels of his Crown:) It encreaſeth Merchants, and makes them great: It enricheth the Shopkeepers, and makes them wealthy: It encourageth Shipping, and Navigation, that carries out the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures of <hi>England,</hi> and returns with rich Commodities,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57825:9"/>and with Gold, and Silver: It ſets thouſands of hands at work, and imploys the poor of the Land; it encourageth Strangers, and Forreigners to come and dwell amongſt us, to ſhew us their art and skill: It advanceth the price of Land, that the Nobles, and Gentry have ſo great a part of. This ſhews the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Trade, that extends its benefits to every man. Now they that are for the keeping up of the Penal Statutes, are not the Friends of the Common-wealth, but Enemies to Trade, becauſe they are for Perſecution. Now he that runs may read, and he that reads may ſee the evil of theſe Penal Laws.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to the Objections that are uſually made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the taking away of theſe Laws, and anſwer them. The firſt Objection is this: Do you think that this Liberty and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration which you now enjoy, is granted and given to you in love and kindneſs; is it not to ſerve a turn, and to bring about another thing? Now my anſwer to this Objection is this; If this work be of God, then it is in love and kindneſs to the Diſſenters: But this work is of God, as will appear to all men, that do but conſider well theſe three things, that is, the time, the way, and the effects. Firſt then of the time; when this King came to the Crown, what were mens thoughts then? The Sufferers they thought, that their condition would have been worſe; the Perſecutors they thought that their Trade would have been better: The Sufferers they did not expect to have enjoyed that which they now enjoy; it was above their Faith, and beyond their hopes. The Perſecutors they did not believe, nor fear, that they ſhould have ſeen, and beheld the things they now ſee. This great diſappointment hath filled the one with joy and gladneſs, and the other with rage and madneſs. God hath overtaken his People with preventing mercies, and hath reproved his enemies in the way; he hath opened the mouths of this people to bleſs God, and the King for this Liberty grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, and hath tyed up the hands of Perſecutors, and this makes them blaſpheme. O let men praiſe the Lord for his wondrous works, and let them know that the moſt High God doth whatſoever he pleaſeth in the Kingdoms of men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 135.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57825:10"/>2. Of the way; other Kings have given Liberty of Conſcience to their Subjects, becauſe they were of their perſuaſions; but this King gives Liberty of Conſcience to all his Proteſtant Subjects, though himſelf be of another perſuaſion; and in this he out-ſhines in glory all the Crowned Heads that were before him. The King thinks that our perſwaſion is the wrong, and we believe that his is not the right, nevertheleſs this does not leſſen his Power, and Authority over us, nor dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our Duty and Obedience to him. God hath put this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heart of the King, that all the Yokes, and Bonds, and Burthens, that have been laid upon Conſcience, or on men for their Conſcience ſake towards God, in the former Reigns to be broken, and for ever removed. Is not this a wonderful work of God, to have all this done at once, which could never be done before, and we have reaſon to think that it would never have been done by any Prince but this? O let no man ſay, that there is a new King riſen up that knew not <hi>Joſeph,</hi> or that there is a <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the Land, that will not know <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> O let this Liberty be thankfully received, and wiſely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, that Gods glory may be advanced, that the Juſtice, wiſdom, kindneſs, and goodneſs of the King, may be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, as the great inſtrument in the hand of God, in a work ſo great and good as this is towards his People.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of the effects, no man can ſay now in this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that the Gates of Liberty are ſhut up againſt him: <hi>The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Nation that keeps the truth may now enter in.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.2.</note> No man can ſay now in theſe Kingdoms, <hi>That the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffers violence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.13.</note> Every Man may now enter into it that will. No Man can ſay now in City, or Countrey, that the evil Angels hold the Winds, that they cannot blow, that is, Perſecutors: Every Man may now ſit under the breathings of Gods Spirit in the Miniſtry of the Word,<note place="margin">Rev. 7.1.</note> and ſerve him without fear. Many hundreds have been let out of Priſon, that were before ſhut up: many thouſands that were before troubled and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, are now quiet, and in peace: many hundreds are now Labouring in the Lords Vineyard, preaching the Word of God up and down every where, and there be many thouſands
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57825:10"/>of Souls, that do attend and hear the Word of God preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them. Have not many thouſands of the People in theſe Nations own'd, and acknowledged this to be the Work of God in their Addreſſes to the King? Now by all this you may ſee, that it is the work of God, then it is in love and kindneſs to the Diſſenters; let this then ſerve for an Anſwer to this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Objection is: If theſe Penal Laws ſhould be taken away, then Popery will come in upon us. By this Objection then I perceive the thing that you fear, is the coming in of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and the way that you will take to keep it out, is to continue the Penal Laws: Now this being an evil way, may bring that evil upon you which you fear:<note place="margin">Numb. 13.28. <hi>to</hi> 33.</note> This evil way the Iſraelites of old did take when they were afraid of the Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites: <hi>And they ſaid one to another, Let us make a Captain, and let us return into Egypt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 14 4. Verſe 29. 1 Cor. 10.</note> Now this being an evil way, brought that evil upon them which they feared; <hi>Your carcaſſes ſhall fall in this wilderneſs.</hi> This evil way did King <hi>Saul</hi> take when he was afraid of the <hi>Philiſtines: Then ſaid</hi> Saul <hi>unto his ſervants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.5, 8, 9. Verſe 7.</note> 
               <hi>Seek me a woman that hath a familiar Spirit, that I may go to her, and enquire of her; and his ſervants ſaid unto him, Behold there is a woman that hath a familiar Spirit at</hi> Endor. Now this being an evil way, brought that evil upon him and his Sons which he feared. <hi>So</hi> Saul <hi>died, and his three Sons, and his Armour-bearer, and all his Men that ſame day together,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.4, 5, 6. This was the evil way that King <hi>Zedekiah</hi> did take, when he was afraid of the <hi>Chaldaeans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 38.19.20.</note> he would not hearken to the word of the Lord by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet; <hi>But he fled, and went forth out of the City by night, by the way of the King's Gardens, by the Gate betwixt two walls, and he went out the way of the Plain, Jer.</hi> 39.4. This being an evil way, did bring upon him and his houſe all that evil which he feared. <hi>Then the King of</hi> Babylon <hi>ſlew the Sons of</hi> Zedekiah <hi>before his eyes in</hi> Riblah, <hi>and he ſlew all the Nobles of</hi> Judah, <hi>and he put out</hi> Zedekiahs <hi>eyes, and bound him in Chains, to carry him to</hi> Babylon, <hi>Jer.</hi> 39.6.7. This evil way did the <hi>Jews</hi> take in the days of our Saviour, and in the days of the Apoſtles, when they were afaid of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 11.48.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57825:11"/>
               <hi>ſhall come, and take away both our Place and Nation.</hi> To ſave themſelves from the <hi>Romans,</hi> they kept up Perſecution, and did ſlay Gods faithful Witneſſes,<note place="margin">Mat. 23 35. Acts 7.32.</note> and were betrayers and murderers, and did endeavour to overthrow the work of God, and the faith of the Goſpel.<note place="margin">Luke 21 6, 26.</note> Now this being an evil way alſo, brought all that evil upon them which they feared. And are you ſtill for the keeping up of compelling and perſecuting Laws, becauſe you are afraid of Popery? Is this the way to keep it out? Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet did any people take an evil way to ſave themſelves from the evil they feared, but it brought it upon them. I have here ſhewed you this at large, and I have alſo ſhewed you the evil of theſe Penal Laws: Take heed therefore leſt you bring upon your ſelves that evil which hath befaln others; you muſt not keep up that which is bad for fear of worſe, you muſt not do evil that good may come of it, you muſt not commit ſin to keep out Popery, you muſt not keep mens Conſciences in Chains for ever, that is the work of the next World, and not this; the Goſpel will not allow that any man ſhould ſuffer in his Body, or in his Eſtate, by perſecuting Laws, for the errors of his mind, nor that any man ſhould forfeit his Free-hold for being of a wrong perſwaſion. He that ſpake as never man ſpake, ſaid, <hi>Let the Wheat and the Tares grow both together until the Harveſt, Mat.</hi> 13.30.<note place="margin">Mat. 15 13. John 16.8. 2 Cor. 5.11.</note> It is Gods work to pull up, the Spirits work to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, it is mans work to perſwade by ſound arguments, and to allure by a good Converſation men from a bad Religion to a better, and from a wrong Religion to the right. A man does not believe as others believe, and cannot believe as others would have him believe, but he believes as he ſees cauſe to believe. The queſtion then is not ſo much what hath been done, nor what ſome men would have to be done, but what is beſt to be done to keep out Popery, for that is your fear. If I ſhould give you counſel will you hearken to it, and if I give you advice will you take it?</p>
            <p>Firſt then if you will keep out Popery, do you <hi>amend your ways and your doings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 7.3.</note> 
               <hi>and turn unto the Lord by a true and ſincere repentance.</hi> You have heard of the Judgments of God which have been abroad in other Lands, and you have been told of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57825:11"/>the Judgments of God at home in this Land; but theſe paſt Judgments have not humbled you, nor your preſent Mercies have not drawn you, nor led you to the God of your Mercies. Do you look like a people brought forth in a day of light? do you look like a people that have lived in a Land of knowledge? do you look like a people that have ſat under the preaching of the Goſpel, and have enjoyed the means of grace ſo long? Were ever mens mouths ſo full of Curſing and Swearing, and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming as now? were ever mens hearts ſo full of Wrath and Rage, Enmity and Hatred againſt God, and againſt his holy ways as now? were ever mens lives ſo full of Unrighteouſneſs and Ungodlineſs, and all Wickedneſs whatſoever, as they are now? Did ever Pride ſo reign in <hi>England,</hi> and Drunkenneſs ſo abound, Murders ſo frequent, and Whoring as it were a Staple Trade? were ever people ſo Debauched and Prophane as they are now? What do you think will become of ſuch a people? <hi>Let no man deceive you with vain words, for becauſe of theſe things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of diſobedience, Eph.</hi> 5.6. O let the cry of your Prayers out-cry the cry of your ſins, that your tears may quench that fire which your ſins have kindled: And be not out-done by Heathens; Remember what <hi>Nineveh</hi> did: <hi>If my people which are called by my name, ſhall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves and pray, and ſeek my face, and turn from their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ways, then I will hear from Heaven, and will forgive their ſin, and will heal their Land,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron,</hi> 7.14. When the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſo provoked the Lord God by their ſins and wickedneſs, their Ark then could not ſave them, nor their Temple could not then preſerve them, but ſwift deſtruction came upon them. O break off your ſins by repentance, and your iniquities by bringing forth fruits of righteouſneſs, that every man may live in Piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, in Loyalty towards his Prince, and in Love and Charity one towards another. The exerciſing ſo many cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon Diſſenters heretofore, and of late years, by pernicious Laws hath opened a door to let in Debauchery upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Land.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly if you will keep out Popery, then let the Clergy of this Land keep out Lazineſs and Idleneſs, Drunkenneſs and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57825:12"/>Pride, Covetouſneſs and Ambition, and Superſtition out of their Tribe, that they may be ſhining and burning lights amongſt the people, and not like the idle Shepherds of old, nor like the greedy and covetous Prieſts that look'd for their gain from their quarter,<note place="margin">Joh. 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.11. Nor like the Hireling that flies from the Sheep when the Wolf comes, but to be valiant for the truth, labouring in Word and Doctrine, taking all opportunities to Preach the Word of God in Seaſon, and out of Seaſon, to the people, with all Authority, with all Sincerity, with all Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with all Humility and Plainneſs; rightly dividing the Word of Truth, and wiſely applying it to the Conſciences of their Hearers; convincing men by ſound Arguments drawn from the Scriptures of Truth, and alluring men by their good Examples and heavenly Converſations, that they may adorn the Goſpel of Chriſt, Praying without ceaſing, Faſting often, Watching diligently over their Flocks, that they may ſave themſelves and them that hear them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, Let them conſider the End of Preaching, which is to enlighten men in the truth, and to build them up in the moſt holy Faith,<note place="margin">Acts 26.18.</note> 
                  <hi>That they may be turned from darkneſs to light and from the power of Satan unto God,</hi> that the bad may be made good, and that the good may be made better, and they that are without, may be brought in, and they that are within may be built up, and encreaſe in grace.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly, Let them conſider the meſſage they are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the People, which was from the beginning, <hi>That God is light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and love, and in him is no darkneſs at all. Behold what manner of love the father hath beſtowed on us, that we ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Sons of God,</hi> John 3.1. <hi>But God commendeth his love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, in that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for us,</hi> Rom. 5.8. <hi>For God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life.</hi> John 3.16. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him that loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own bloud. Rev.</hi> 1.5. The Meſſage then is love, the love of God to men on earth, Peace and good Will; this love is ſhed abroad in the Heart, this love draws men to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57825:12"/>God, and keeps them with him, and carrys them to him.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.35.</note> O what a bleſſed ſubject is the love of God for Men to dwell upon!</item>
               <item>3. Thirdly, Let them conſider the Charge that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their care, to overſee the Souls of ſo many thouſands of Men and Women, that do hear them, and will hear none but them in this Kingdom. <hi>Wherefore I take you to record this day, that I am pure from the blood of all men; for I have not ſhunned to declare unto you all the counſel of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Ezek. 3.20.</note> 
                  <hi>take heed therefore unto your ſelves, and unto all the flock, over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers. Acts</hi> 20.26, 27, 28.</item>
               <item>4. Fourthly, Let them conſider of that Account they muſt give to God almighty hereafter; <hi>Who ſhall give Account to him that is ready to judge the Quick and the Dead.</hi> 1 Peter 4.5. <hi>So then every one of us ſhall give Account of himſelf to God,</hi> Rom. 14.12. <hi>But I keep under my Body, and bring it into ſubjection, leſt that by any means when I have Preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. O let theſe things be well conſidered of by the Clergy-men, if they have been in the wrong heretofore, that they may be in the right now. In ſome things we offend in all, in all things we offend in ſome; if this be not regarded, by them, it will be a witneſs againſt them; the leſs of the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of man that is ſeen in it, the more of the power of God may appear by it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thirdly, If you will keep out Popery when it ſhall pleaſe the King to call a Parliament, that you do then chuſe ſuch men for your Repreſentatives, that may perfect this good work the King hath begun, for Liberty of Conſcience, chuſe men that have a good affection for the Kings gracious Declaration, Men of Wiſdom and Underſtanding, Men of good Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, Men that have a high value for Religion, and a true love for their Countrey, Men that have lived peaceably, and quietly amongſt their Neighbours, that are not of a Perſecuting Spirit. The King hath been graciouſly pleaſed to offer that to his People, that is ſo great, and the way of doing it ſo Juſt,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57825:13"/>that no Prince can offer better, and no People can deſire more. The thing the King offers is Liberty, Liberty of Conſcience, the free exerciſe of every mans Conſcience towards God; a thing that hath been ſo much deſired, a thing that is ſo highly valued, a thing ſo well pleaſing to God, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable with Men, a thing that hath made Nations great and happy, that this Liberty of Conſcience which we all enjoy may be ſo ſecured to all by ſuch a Law, that it may not be in the power of any that ſhall come after to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſettlement, nor deſtroy that ſecurity. Now the way the King offers this is in your own way, in a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary way, and can there be any thing more Juſt than this, that by them theſe Penal Laws and Teſts may be taken away, and that by them ſuch a Law may be made, as may ſecure Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience to every Man, that it may not be in the power of any one party to hurt the reſt for the exerciſing of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences towards God in his worſhip. Did ever Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hurt any Nation? or did ever Liberty of Conſcience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Religion? Have not the benefits &amp; bleſſings been ever great that have flowed from it, as I have fully proved before? Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, ſome oppoſe this good work, others do diſcourage it, and ſome do not underſtand it: under theſe many difficulties doth Liberty of Conſcience ſtruggle at this day, and wants ſtrength to be brought forth. The King hath put his Royal Hand to this good work, and he expects that his Subjects ſhould put their Hands to it alſo; that when a Parliament ſhall be called, and come together, they may compleat it, and perfect it.<note place="margin">John 3.9.</note> If any ſhall ſay, as <hi>Nicodemus, How can theſe things be?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that which hath been done may be done, now this hath been done by Heathens themſelves. <hi>Now O King eſtabliſh the decree and ſign the writing, that it may not be changed according to the Law of the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians <hi>which altereth not. Dan. 6.8. Then they came near, and ſpake before the King concerning the Kings Decree, Haſt thou not ſigned a decree, that every man that ſhall ask a petition of any God or Man within Thirty days ſave of thee, O King, ſhall be caſt into the Den of Lyons? The King anſwered and ſaid, the thing is true according to the Law of the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians <hi>which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth not, verſe</hi> 12. <hi>Then the King when he heard theſe words, was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57825:13"/>ſore diſpleaſed with himſelf, and ſet his Heart on</hi> Daniel <hi>to deliver him: and he laboured till the going down of the Sun to deliver him. verſe</hi> 14. Here was a Law made that could not be changed, nor altered, they that made it would not do it, and the King that ſigned it could not do it, though he laboured till the going down of the Sun. This was done by Heathens, ſurely Chriſtians can do much more.</p>
            <p>And was there not a Law made in <hi>England</hi> heretofore, that you call <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and notwithſtanding the many Changes, and Alterations, that have been in this Kingdom ſince that, is that Law changed or altered? The People of this Kingdom here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, have been in great confuſions, and in great diſtraction under many Calamities, and Judgments; in War, and Blood, in Flames, and Perſecutions, yet <hi>Magna Charta</hi> hath remained, and doth ſtill; why then may there not be a <hi>Magna Charta</hi> for Liberty, as well as there is for Property?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If you will keep out Popery, then you muſt keep out ſlaviſh fear, and groundleſs Jealouſys and unbelief out of your hearts, and minds. Fear God and keep his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, truſt in the Lord for ever, <hi>For in the Lord Jehovah is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſtrength: Iſaiah</hi> 26.4. <hi>The Lord God is a Wall of Fire, round about his People, and the glory in the midſt of them, Zachary, chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 5. And if there were as many Enemies as there be Sands in the Sea, they could not break through this Wall to hurt you. <hi>What ſhall one then anſwer the Meſſengers of the Nation? That the Lord hath founded</hi> Zion, <hi>and the poor of his People ſhall truſt in it, Iſa.</hi> 14.32. God hath builded his church upon a Rock,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> and the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it. Can men meaſure the Flames, can men bundle up the Air, can men turn the earth into a lump of Gold? They may as ſoon do this, as prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Church. Look into the Days of the Apoſtles, the Church of God in that day had no Emperours nor Kings to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect it, nor humane Laws to ſupport it, nor Carnal Weapons to defend it, they had no Armies to guard them, nor to fight their Battles, but both <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> were againſt them. <hi>But the unbelieving</hi> Jews <hi>ſtirred up the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and made their minds evil affected againſt the Brethren, and there was an aſſault made both of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>and alſo of the</hi> Jews, <hi>with their Rulers, to uſe them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57825:14"/>deſpitefully, and to ſtone them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7.52.</note> 
               <hi>Acts.</hi> 14.2, 5. <hi>yet in all this, they were more than Conquerours.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 19.28.</note> The great <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> fell down before them, and the Temple worſhip of the <hi>Jews</hi> came to nought. <hi>By the Shield of Faith they ſubdued Kingdoms,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.33.</note> and by the Sword of the Spirit they conquered Nations. <hi>For the Weapons of our War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, are not carnal, but mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds; caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. I need not tell you what men have done, I cannot tell you what men will do; but I can tell you what men cannot do: <hi>Behold I have ſet before thee an open door and no man can ſhut it, Rev.</hi> 3.8. No man can ſhut the door of Faith, the door of hope, the door of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel grace,<note place="margin">Acts 5.39.</note> that God hath ſet open, no man can overthrow that work, which God hath begun, and hath been carrying on in theſe Nations. <hi>The Phariſees therefore ſaid among themſelves, Perceive ye how ye prevail nothing? Behold, the World is gone after him, Acts</hi> 12.19. No man can bring any evil upon you, that God cannot prevent, nor hinder that good from you, that God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to you. No man can take from you that Joy that God gives to you, Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory; <hi>and your Joy no man taketh from you, John</hi> 16.22. No man can hinder the fulfilling of Gods word, the accompliſhment of the prophecies, <hi>and the finiſhing of the myſtery of God, as he hath declared to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets, Rev.</hi> 10.7. No man can hinder the working of Providences, which God doth exerciſe in the Government of the World, for the good of his People. No man can hinder the increaſe of grace here, nor the reward of glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. I have here ſhewed you what that work of God was in the days of old, and I have ſhewed you, what that work of God is in our day; I have alſo ſhewed you the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of theſe Penal Laws, and have anſwered the Objections; that are uſually made againſt their being taken away, I have alſo ſhewed you, how Popery may be kept out of this Kingdom, and it may be love may ſay I have ſaid too little, and envy may ſay I have ſaid too much; and who can pleaſe all? My deſign in all this, is the glory of God, the honour of the King and the good of all his ſubjects; <hi>Love the brother-hood. Fear God. Honour the King,</hi> 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.17.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:57825:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>IT is often alledged, That if the Teſt ſhould be taken away, then the Papiſts will come and ſit in Parliament.</p>
            <p>But how can the Papiſts ſit in the Houſe of Commons, unleſs the Proteſtants chuſe them? How can they enter within them Walls, unleſs the Proteſtants open the Door, being in number more than two hundred to one Papiſt, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Land. Is it not very unlikely at this time, that Proteſtants will chuſe Papiſts for their Repreſentatives in Parliament? Will they not rather chuſe Men of their own Perſuaſions, that are moſt agreeable to their own Sentiments, from whom they may expect to reap the greateſt
<pb facs="tcp:57825:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>benefits, eſpecially in a matter ſo great and weighty as this is? You therefore that are for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Penal Laws and Teſts, let me then ask you theſe following Queſtions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Whether the many Teſts that have been made in this Kingdom, theſe many years paſt, did ever ſupport, and preſerve the Makers of them?</item>
               <item>II. Whether theſe Teſts be not Penal Laws?</item>
               <item>III. Whether the preſent Teſts be not againſt Religion and Liberty, which are ſo dear to all Men?</item>
               <item>IV. How was Religion preſerved, and kept up in this Kingdom, before theſe two late Teſts were made?</item>
               <item>V. Whether the Penal Laws and Teſts have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd Religion in this Nation, ſince they were made, or deſtroyed it?</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57825:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>VI. Whether the Penal Laws and Teſts, be then the Bulwark of the Proteſtant Religion againſt Popery?</item>
               <item>VII. Whether you can find any Men, that have been Perſecutors, and Spoilers of others, for their Conſciences towards God, that are for the taking away Penal Laws and Teſts?</item>
               <item>VIII. Whether that be a True Church, that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports her ſelf by Perſecuting Laws, and enricheth her ſelf by the Ruin of others?</item>
               <item>IX. Whether Liberty of Conſcience be not the Intereſt of this Nation?</item>
               <item>X. Whether a Parliament may not be capable of finding out a better way, and a better ſecurity for our Liberty, and Religion, than theſe Teſts are?</item>
               <item>XI. Whether the Church of God hath not a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Refuge, and a ſtronger Tower to flie unto at all times, than Humane Laws, or an Arm of Fleſh? <hi>The Lord alſo will be a Refuge for the oppreſſed; a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge
<pb facs="tcp:57825:16"/>in time of trouble,</hi> Pſal. 9.9. <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength, and my ſhield; my heart truſted in him, and I am helped,</hi> Pſal. 28.7. <hi>Our Soul waiteth for the Lord, he is our help, and our ſhield,</hi> Pſal. 33.20. <hi>For thou haſt been a ſhelter for me, and a ſtrong Tower from the Enemy,</hi> Pſal. 61.3. <hi>In God is my ſalvation, and my glory: The Rock of my ſtrength, and my Refuge is in God,</hi> Pſal. 62.7. <hi>My Goodneſs, and my Fortreſs, my high Tower, and my Deliverer, my Shield, and he in whom I truſt; who ſubdueth my People under me,</hi> Pſal. 144.2. <hi>Ye that fear the Lord, truſt in the Lord, he is their Help, and their Shield,</hi> Pſal. 115.11. <hi>For the Lord God is a Sun and Shield; the Lord will give grace and glory: No good thing will he with-hold from them that walk uprightly,</hi> Pſal. 84.11. <hi>Truſt ye in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength,</hi> Iſa. 26.4.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57825:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
